Finding Aid for Nichols Arboretum (University of Michigan) records, 1921-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Nichols Arboretum (University of Michigan) records
1921-2006
1995-2004
Nichols Arboretum (University of Michigan)
05127 Bimu 2
The Nichols Arboretum consists of 123 acres of land adjacent to the University of Michigan's Central Campus. This collection of the Arboretum's records dates mainly from the latter half of the 20th century, and features publications and printed materials from the 1990s. It also includes written histories from the early 20th century, several files of administrative materials from the late 1960s, and materials pertaining to proposals for the Arboretum grounds in the 1990s
3 linear feet
3 drawers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was transferred by the Nichols Arboretum (Donor No. 8724 ) in 1998, with additions transferred in 2003 and 2013..
The records are open to research.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
Originally intended to be a garden for the Botany Department, the land was later found unsuitable for herbaceous plants. In 1916, the Botany Department moved its garden to a site on Packard Road, and the Nichols land was turned over to the Department of Landscape Design for development as an arboretum.
Today, the Nichols Arboretum consists of 123 acres, and includes notable collections of plants native to Michigan, as well as from around the world. It also includes an educational facility in the Burnham house, which was moved to the Arboretum grounds in 1998, where it became the James D. Reader, Jr. Urban Environmental Education Center.
In 2004, Matthaei Botanical Gardens and Nichols Arboretum were united as a single independent unit of the University of Michigan. A separate record group for Matthaei Botanical Gardens is available at the Bentley Historical Library.
Further information can be found in the Matthaei Botanical Gardens and Nichols Arboretum collection, which covers the records of the units after they combined.
The Nichols Arboretum records comprise of 3 linear feet and 12 oversize folders of materials spanning the years from 1921 to 2006. The bulk of the collection dates from 1995 to 2004. The records document a brief period of the arboretum's administration from the late 1960s, plans and proposals for the arboretum grounds from throughout the late 20th century, and publications and events at the arboretum from the mid-1990s to the very early 2000s. The records have been divided into ten series: Administrative, Correspondence, Display Materials, Events, Friends of NA, Projects, Publications and Printed Materials, Topical Files, Maps, and Plans and Proposals.
Subjects:
Nichols Arboretum (University of Michigan); Landscape architecture--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Gardens--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Natural areas--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Newsletters.; Compact discs.; Sound recordings.
- Administrative
  The Administrative series (0.6 linear feet and one oversize folder) consists mostly of correspondence and work-related files maintained between 1966 and 1969, although it also includes several scattered folders of information from the late 1990s. Several folders of historical material and staff meeting minutes are also included.
  - Academic Advisory Committee, 1999-2002 (Box 1)
  - Acquisitions (Box 1)
  - ARB Provost, 1997; 1999; 2001 (Box 1)
  - Budget, 1992-1997 (Box 1)
  - Educational and research activities, 1998; 2000 (Box 1)
  - Excerpts and summaries of Regents' Proceedings regarding Nichols Arboretum (Box 1)
  - Goals and Objectives, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Grounds Committee, 1999-2003 (Box 1)
  - Histories of Nichols Arboretum and Department of Landscape Design / Architecture, 1935-1945; undated (Box 1)
  - Lists of Maps and Proposals (Box 1)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1991-1993 (Box 1)
  - Meeting notes on Arboretum mission, goals, strengths and threats, circa 2001 (Map-case 240, Folder 1)
  - Mountain Bike Problem, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Personnel, 1935-1945 (Box 1)
  - Police Reports, Damage and Restitution, 1970-1988 (Box 1)
  - Policies, 1934-1999 (Box 1)
  - Position Analyses undated post-1968Word-processed lists of maps and proposals, undated (Box 1)
  - Programming, 1997-2003 (Box 1)
  - Public Relations, 1991-1993 (Box 1)
  - Public Safety, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Rules of the Arb (Box 1)
  - Sanitary Sewage, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Security and Vandalism, 1928-1994 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Space Management, 2001-2002 (Box 1)
  - Staff, 1994-2004 (Box 1)
  - Staff and Committees, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Staff Duties, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Staff Meetings, 1988-2001; 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Steering Committee, 1972-1989 (Box 1)
  - Stewardship, 2002 (Box 1)
  - Strategic Planning, 1999-2001 (Box 1)
  - Survey, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Theft Reward, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Tribute Committee, 2002 (Box 1)
  - Usage Studies, 1988-2000 (Box 1)
  - Visitor Survey, 1988-2000 (Box 1)
  - Work activity reports, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Work Orders, 2000-2002 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (0.2 linear feet) contains communications to and from the faculty of the Nichols Arboretum, as well as topical correspondence regarding information about the President's House and the closing of Nichols Drive.
  - Brady, James J., 1992 (Box 1)
  - Braman, Arlie, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Closing Nichols Drive, 1974-1989 (Box 1)
  - Donor Letters, 1993; 1997-1998; 2004 (Box 1)
  - Elliott, Marian J., 1994 (Box 1)
  - General, 1991; 1997; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Hanson, Richard (Asst. Prof. of Landscape Arch.) to Walter Chambers (Director of Nichols Arboretum), 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - President's House, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Wilson, Michelle, 1993 (Box 1)
- Display Materials
  The Display Materials series (0.2 linear feet and one oversize folder) consists of items that were used as informational displays at the arboretum. Of particular note in this series are clippings from the arboretum's regular column in the Ann Arbor News from 1994 and 1995, and a display that included several photographs of volunteers.
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Volunteers and Friends of Nichols Arboretum, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Wild Ones Conference, 2000 (Box 1)
  - "Winter in the Arb-Beauty and the Beast" (Box 1)
  - Laminated map showing trails and benches, undated (Map-case 240, Folder 2)
  - Laminated map showing trail distances, undated (Map-case 240, Folder 2)
- Events
  The Events series (0.3 linear feet) contains information about the various programs and events put on at the arboretum. This includes workshops, the 5K run, the Centennial, and Shakespeare at the Arb.
  - 5K Run, 2003 (Box 2)
  - Backyard Wildlife Habitat Tour, 2001 (Box 2)
  - Borders Benefit Days, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Centennial, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Conifer Tree Sale, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Environmental Education Program, 1997 (Box 2)
  - "Imagine/Align,", 2004 (Box 2)
  - MI Big Ten Run, 2004; 2006 (Box 2)
  - Natural Areas Workshop, 2000-2001; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - NRE 445 Activities, 1995-1998 (Box 2)
  - Shakespeare in the Arb -- "A Midsummer Night's Dream,", 2002; 2005 (Box 2)
  - Sustainable Architecture, 2001 (Box 2)
  - UM Art Department Activities, 1997-2002 (Box 2)
  - Winter Sports, 1921-1994 (Box 2)
- Friends of Nichols Arboretum
  The Friends of NA series (0.7 linear feet) consists of information from the Friends of the Nichols Arboretum organization. The series primarily consists of information from meetings of the board of directors.
  - Annual Meeting, 1998-2001; 2003; 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Award, 1997 (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors, 1990-2004; 15 folders (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors Annual Lists, 1991-2004 (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors Meeting Papers, 2002-2003 (Box 2)
  - Board Responsibilities (Box 2)
  - Budget, 1999-2000 (Box 2)
  - Bylaws, 1991; 1992; 2002 (Box 2)
  - Charter Members, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Financial Reports, 1991-1994 (Box 2)
  - Formation, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Fundraising and Development, 1994-1997 (Box 2)
  - Initial Member Solicitation, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Meetings, 1989-1994 (Box 2)
  - Member List, 1993; 1995 (Box 2)
  - Membership, 1990-1992 (Box 2)
  - Mission Statement, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Recruitment Letters, 1993-1997 (Box 2)
  - Welcome Letter, 1997 (Box 2)
- Projects
  The Projects series (0.5 linear feet) contains information on the various developmental projects at the arboretum, including construction projects and specific site development. This includes sites such as the Appalachian Glen and the development of the walkways through the medical campus.
  - Amphitheater Project, 2004 (Box 3)
  - Appalachian Glen, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Burnham House/Gateway Garden Development, 1995-1999 (Box 3)
  - Conrail Underpass, 1994-1995 (Box 3)
  - Dow Field Prairie Burns, 1998-2000 (Box 3)
  - Dow Prairie, 1993-1994 (Box 3)
  - Gateway Garden Development, 2002 (Box 3)
  - Gateway Garden -- Iron Fence, 1998-2002 (Box 3)
  - General, 1981-1992 (Box 3)
  - Horticultural Programs, 1955 (Box 3)
  - "Landscape Explorers" Project, 2003-2004 (Box 3)
  - Medical Campus Walkways, 2002 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Heritage Route, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Plant Collection -- Appalachian Glen (Box 3)
  - Residential College Projects, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Rhododendron Glen, 1991 (Box 3)
  - School Girl's Glen, 1973-2003 (Box 3)
  - Student Projects, 1992-1998; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Study Center, 1963-1965; 1968 (Box 3)
  - Study Center Promotion (Box 3)
  - Tunnel between Park, 2000 (Box 3)
  - Urban Environmental Education Center, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Washington Heights Road, 1992-1998 (Box 3)
  - Work Space, 1964-1979 (Box 3)
- Publications and Printed Material
  The Publications and Printed Materials series (0.2 linear feet and one oversize folder) consists of items printed or published by the Arboretum or the Friends of Nichols Arboretum. The bulk of the items are pamphlets, mailers or publicity materials from the 1990s and early 2000s. Nearly a full run of Tree Line, the newsletter of the Friends of Nichols Arboretum is collected in this series. Tree Line is useful for the information it provides on significant events that occurred between 1991 and 2004, such as the acquisition of the Burnham House and its transformation into an educational center. Other items of interest include guides to the Peony Garden from 1995 and 2000, and a list of plant donations with location information.
  A non-exhaustive list of items about the Arboretum that were published by entities other than the Arboretum or the Friends has been included below. These items were previously acquired by the Bentley Historical Library and are separately cataloged.
  - 8 1/2" x 11" flyers, 1993-2003 (Box 3)
  - Educational program announcements and material, 1995-1999 (Box 3)
  - Events materials, 1995-2004 (Box 3)
  - Event posters, 1993-2004 (Map-case 240, Folder 3)
  - Fundraising and Volunteer Opportunities, 1996; 1999 undated (Box 3)
  - General brochures, etc., undated (Box 3)
  - Guides to local arboreta, gardens and educational organizations, 1995; undated (Box 3)
  - Lists and bloom information regarding plants in Arboretum, 1996; undated (Box 3)
  - Master Plan, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Peony Garden Guide, 1995; 2000 (Box 3)
  - Tree Line
    (Newsletter of the Friends of Nichols Arboretum)
    - 1991-1995 (Box 3)
    - 1996-1999 (Box 3)
    - 2000-2002 (Box 3)
    - 2003-2004 (Box 3)
  - Urban Environmental Education Center, 1994-1999; undated (Box 3)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series (0.3 linear feet) includes items that do not fall easily under any of the other series. These include the original design drawing for the Arboretum's main gate and the guest comment book from Arbfest 2001, as well as press clippings and lists of various plants acquired by the arboretum.
  - Aerial Photographs (oversize) (Box 3)
  - Arb Alumni, 2005 (Box 3)
  - Arbfest guest comment book, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Arboretum Videos, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Design for gates by the Department of Landscape Design, oversize (Box 3)
  - Dow Field Species List (Box 3)
  - Drawing of Burnham House by Kemnitz, undated; oversize (Box 3)
  - Friends of Stinchfield Woods, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Hiroshima Plant Exchange, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Maps, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 2000 (Box 3)
  - Original of Nichols Arboretum logo, circa 1990; oversize (Box 3)
  - Peony Flowers, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Photograph of Entrance, 1922 (Box 3)
  - Plant Records (Box 3)
  - Press Clippings, 1952-1964 (Box 3)
  - Signage, 1990-1994 (Box 3)
  - Sounds of the Arb, 2003; CD (Box 3)
  - Website Development, 2000-2002 (Box 3)
  - Woody Plant Material, 1991 (Box 3)
- Maps
  The Maps series (four oversize folders) includes maps of the Arboretum as it existed at particular times. Of particular note in this series are a topographical map from 1947, a map of the Peony Garden from 2000, and a plant locations map from 1997. Several additional maps can be found in the Display Materials series. A list of other maps of the Arboretum that were previously acquired and catalogued by the University of Michigan Libraries is included below.
  - Copy of June 1961 map of Arboretum, with indications added for forests, erosion, sled runs, high use areas and property lines, undated (Map-case 240, Folder 4)
  - Copy of June 1961 map of Arboretum, with indications added for Ann Arbor City Park property and potential building sites, undated (Map-case 240, Folder 4)
  - Planting Scheme, 1921 (Map-case 240, Folder 4)
  - 1927 Planting Scheme map, with foot trails added in red pencil, undated (Map-case 240, Folder 5)
  - Topographical Maps, 1917-1961 (Map-case 240, Folder 4a)
  - Topographical Map of Nichols Arboretum, 1943 (Map-case 240, Folder 5)
  - Map of Arboretum showing location of 64 specimens, 1997 (Map-case 240, Folder 5)
  - Peony Garden by A. Arscott, 2000 (Map-case 240, Folder 5)
  - Peony Garden Identification Chart, 1927 (Map-case 240, Folder 5)
  - Peony Garden (draft) (Map-case 240, Folder 5)
  - Nichols Arboretum, undated (Map-case 240, Folder 5)
  - Proposed Winter Sports Arena, 1927 (Map-case 240, Folder 5)
- Plans and Proposals
  The Plans and Proposals series (five oversize folders) also consists mainly of maps of the Arboretum. Unlike the Maps series, however, many of the items depicted in the Plans and Proposals series never came to exist. Although most of the items in this series date from the late 1990s, it also includes a set of drawings from 1965 showing different perspectives along the First Trail.
  - Appalachian Cove (Map-case 240, Folder 10)
  - Service Road, 1947 (Map-case 240, Folder 6)
    (depicts existing and proposed topography)
  - "The First Trail" by the Department of Landscape Architecture, 1965; mounted on six presentation boards
    - "The First Trail" by the Department of Landscape Architecture, 1965 (Map-case 241, Folder 7)
    - "The First Trail" by the Department of Landscape Architecture, 1965 (Map-case 241, Folder 8)
      (continued)
  - Copies of June 1961 map of Arboretum, showing alternative sites for a "Study Center," undated (Map-case 241, Folder 8)
  - Arboretum Extension Plan, 1997 (Map-case 242, Folder 10)
  - Burnham house as planned and with two parking alternatives, undated (Map-case 242, Folder 11)
  - Interpretive Center Proposal by CG Kunkle, 1992 (Map-case 242, Folder 11)
  - Riverfront designed by Susan Litts, 2000 (Map-case 242, Folder 11)
  - Conceptual diagram of problems and solutions, undated (Map-case 242, Folder 11)
  - Topographic analysis and potential land use, undated (Map-case 242, Folder 11)
- Miscellaneous
  - Aerial Photographs [folder 14] (Map-case 242, Folder 14)
  - Design for gates by the Department of Landscape Design, undated (Map-case 242, Folder 12)
  - Drawing of Burnham House by Kemnitz, undated (Map-case 242, Folder 13)
  - Federated Commemorative Wild Flower Garden, 1955 (Map-case 242, Folder 13)
  - Original of Nichols Arboretum logo, circa 1990 (Map-case 242, Folder 13)
Related Material:
Arboretum Maps
Topographical survey of grounds for botanical garden, Ann Arbor, Mich. Published: Chicago, Ill.: O.C. Simonds, 1906. Location: Hatcher Graduate Map Library Rare Cases -- Ask at desk Rm. 825S, Call No.: G 4114 .A8:2N5 1906 .O12
Plat of grounds, Botanical Garden, Ann Arbor, Mich. Published: Chicago, Ill.: O.C. Simonds, 1906. Location: Bentley Historical Library, Call No.: M 4114.A8:2N5 1906 C2
Identification chart of the herbaceous peony collection, Nichols Arboretum. Published: Ann Arbor, Mich.: Dept. of Landscape Design, University of Michigan, 1927. Location: Bentley Historical Library, Call No.: M4114.A8:2N5 1927 U5
Identification chart of the herbaceous peony collection, Nichols Arboretum. Published: Ann Arbor, Mich.: Dept. of Landscape Design, University of Michigan, 1929. Location: Bentley Historical Library, Call No.: M4114.A8:2N5 1929 U5
Identification chart of the herbaceous peony collection, Nichols Arboretum. Published: Ann Arbor, Mich.: Dept. of Landscape Design, University of Michigan, 1937. Location: Bentley Historical Library, Call No.: M4114.A8:2N5 1937 U5
The general planting scheme of Nichols Arboretum. Published: Ann Arbor, Mich.: Dept. of Landscape Design, University of Michigan, 1927. Location: Bentley Historical Library, Call No.: M4114.A8:2N5 1927 U5a
Printed Materials (not exhaustive)
Trees and shrubs hardy in southern Michigan and surrounding territory. Authors: Nichols Arboretum. Published: Ann Arbor, Mich., The University of Michigan, 1937; Location: Bentley Historical Library; Call No.: Fimu C457
"The Arb -- Flora, Fauna And Tomfoolery," by Pat Roessle Materka. Published in Michigan Alumnus Vol. 94, No. 6, July/August 1988, p. 20. Location: Bentley Historical Library, Call No.: Fimu H1a.1
"The University Arboretum: A Beautiful Setting for the Study of Plant Life." Published in Michigan Alumnus Vol. 28, No. 23, March 30, 1922, p. 713. Location: Bentley Historical Library, Call No.: Fimu H1a.1
"The Birds of School Girl's Glen Region, Ann Arbor, Michigan; A Study in Local Ornithology," by A.D. Tinker. Published in Michigan Geological and Biological Survey, Lansing, Mich.: 1910. Location: Bentley Historical Library, Call No.: EA 147 T589 B618
The Ann Arbor Observer, June 1995. Location: Bentley Historical Library, Call No. EC 2 A613.5 A613k